you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with
organized religions and ideologies and said
that his only concern was to set
men absolutely unconditionally free. He is
the author of many books, among them
The Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency
of Change, Freedom from the Known, and
The Flight of the Eagle. This is
one of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, in our last
conversation we were beginning to talk
about consciousness and its relation to death
in the context of living as a
total movement. And we even touched
on the word reincarnation toward the end
when we had to draw our conversation to
its conclusion. I do hope that we can
continue there. You see, one of the
factors in death is the mind is
so frightened. We are so frightened of that
very word and nobody talks about it.
I mean, it isn't a daily conversation. It
is something to be avoided, something
that is inevitable. For God's sake, keep
it as far away as possible. We even paint
corpses to make them look as though they're not there.
That's the most absurd thing. Now, what
we are discussing, sir, is, isn't it, the
understanding of death, its relation to
living, and this thing called love. One
cannot possibly understand the immensity, and
it is immense, what this thing called
death, unless there is real freedom from
fear. That's why we talked some time ago
about the problem of fear. Without really
freeing the mind, unless the mind frees
itself from fear, there is no
possibility of understanding the extraordinary beauty,
strength and the vitality of death.
A very, very remarkable way to put it, the vitality
of death, and yet normally we regard it as the
total negation of life.
Right, that's right. So, I mean, if
we are enquiring into this question of death,
fear must be completely non-existent in us. Then I
can proceed, then I can find out what death
means. We touched a little bit on
reincarnation, the belief that is maintained throughout the
East, which has no reality in daily life.
It's like going to church every Sunday and being
mischievous for the rest of the six days.
So, a person who is really serious, really attentive,
goes into this question of death, he must
understand what it means, the quality of it,
not the ending of it. That's what
we are going to discuss a little bit.
The ancient Egyptians, the pharaohs and all the
first dynasty till the 18th and so on, they
prepared for death. They said, we will cross that
river with all our goods, with all our chariots,
with all our belongings, with all our
property, with all our... and therefore their caves,
their tombs were filled with all the things
of their daily life, corn, you know all that.
So, living was only a means to ending dying.
That's one way of looking at it. The other is
reincarnation, which is the Indian-Asian outlook. And
there is this whole idea of resurrection
of the Christians, reborn, carried by Gabriel Angelou
and all that to heaven, and you would be...
Now, what is the fact? These
are all theories, suppositions, beliefs and non-facts.
I mean, supposed to be born,
Jesus come out of the grave,
resurrected physically. That is just a
belief. There were no cameras then.
There were no... ten people say, yes, I
saw it. It's only seven people who saw it.
There were no cameras then.
There were no... ten people say, yes,
I saw it. It's only somebody imagined.
We'll go into that a little bit, a little later.
So, there is this living and preparing for
death, with the ancients, Egyptians, then there is the
reincarnation, then there is resurrection. Now, if
one isn't frightened, you follow, sir, deeply,
then what is death? What is it that
dies, apart from the organism? The organism may continue,
if you look after it very carefully,
for eighty or ninety, a hundred years.
If you have no disease, if you have no
accidents, if there is a way of living sanely,
healthily, perhaps you'll last a hundred years or
a hundred and ten years. And then what?
You follow, sir? You live a hundred years.
For what? For this kind of life? Fighting, quarrelling,
bickering, bitterness, anger, jealousy,
futility, a meaningless existence.
It is meaningless existence, as we are living now.
A. And in terms of our previous
remarks, this is all the content of consciousness.
K. Of consciousness. That's right. Now,
this is all the content of consciousness.
A. Of consciousness. That's right.
Yes.
K. Now, so, what is it that dies?
And what is it one is frightened of?
You follow? What is it one is frightened
of? Death. Losing the known, losing my wife,
losing my house, losing my
– all the things I've acquired,
losing this content of consciousness. You follow?
So, can the content of consciousness be totally be emptied?
You follow, sir?
A. Yes, I do.
K. Which is the living. The dying is the living.
When the content is totally emptied.
That means no attachment.
It is not a brutal cutting
off, but the understanding of attachment,
the understanding of dependency,
the understanding of acquisition,
power, position, anxiety, all that. The
emptying of that is the real death.
The emptying of that is the real death.
And therefore, the emptying
of consciousness means the consciousness
which has created its own limitation
by its content comes to an end.
I wonder if you...
A. Yes, yes. Yes, you have.
I was following you very carefully, and
it occurred to me that there is
a radical relation between birth and death, that the two,
when they are looked upon
as moments in a total cycle,
are not grasped at the depth level
that you are beginning to speak about.
K. Yes, sir.
A. Am I correct?
K. That's correct.
A. Good. Please, please do go on.
K. So, death becomes a
living when the content of consciousness,
which makes its own frontier, its
own limitation, comes to an end.
And this is not a
theory, not a speculative, intellectual grasp,
but the actual perception of attachment.
I am taking that as an example.
Being attached to something, property, man, woman,
the book I have written,
or the knowledge I have acquired,
the attachment, and the battle to be detached,
because attachment breeds pain.
Therefore I say to myself, I
must be detached, and the battle begins.
And the whole content of my consciousness is this,
the battle which we described previously.
Now, can that content be detached?
Now, can that content be emptied, empty itself?
Not emptied by an act of perception.
Empty itself, which means,
can this whole content be
observed with its unconscious content?
You follow, sir?
A. Yes, I do.
K. There is consciousness.
I can be consciously aware
of the content of my consciousness.
My house, my property, my wife, my children, my job,
the things I have acquired, the things I have learnt,
I can be consciously aware of all that.
But also there is deeper content
in the very recesses of my mind,
which is racial, collective, acquired,
the things that unconsciously I have gathered,
the influences, the pressures, the
strains of living in a world
that is corrupt, all that is seeped in,
all that is gathered in there.
A. Both personal and impersonal.
Both personal and impersonal.
This includes then what the depth psychologists are calling
collective consciousness, as well
as the personal consciousness.
K. Collective as well as... So, that is that.
Now, can all that be exposed?
Because this is very important.
Because if I really want to go,
if the mind really wants to understand and grasp
the full meaning of death,
the vastness of it, the great
quality of a mind that says,
yes, that's empty, gives a tremendous vitality, energy.
So, my question is, can the mind be aware totally
of all the content?
As well as the open.
The collective, the personal, the racial, the transitory.
You follow? The whole of that.
Now, we say it is possible through analysis.
A. Yes, we do.
K. I said analysis, paralysis.
Because every analysis must be perfect, complete.
And you are frightened that it may not be complete.
And if you have not completed it,
you carry it over as a memory,
which will then analyse the next incident.
So, each analysis brings its own incompleteness.
Each analysis brings its own incompleteness.
A. Oh, certainly, yes.
K. Therefore it is a total paralysis.
A. In following what you are saying,
I am very taken with
what we usually regard as death,
which has a very clear
relationship to what you have said
about the endless series of analytical acts.
K. Yes, sir.
A. We regard death as a
terminus in terms of a line.
K. Quite. Because we think laterally.
A. We think laterally, exactly.
But what you are saying is, on the contrary,
we must regard this vertically.
And in the regarding of it vertically,
we no longer see – please check
me if I am off here –
we no longer see death as simply a moment
of termination to a certain trajectory of repetition.
But there is a total qualitative change here,
which is not the cessation of something
that we have to regret as
though we had lost something valuable.
K. Yes, I am leaving my wife and children,
and my property, my blasted blank account.
You see, sir, this is really – if
one can go very deeply into this –
there is this content, which is my consciousness,
acquired, inherited, imposed, influenced,
propaganda, attachment, detachment, anxiety,
fear, pleasure, all that.
And also the hidden things.
I am asking myself, since analysis is really paralysis,
not intellectual supposition,
but actually it is not a complete act.
Analysis can never produce a complete act.
The word analysis means to break
up, you know, the breaking up.
A. To loosen up. K. Loosen up, break up.
Therefore I reject that totally.
I won't analyse, because I see the stupidity,
the paralytic process of it.
Then what am I to do? You are following?
Because that is the tradition, introspective,
or paralysis,
or the way of life,
or analysis by myself or by a professional,
which is now the fact, and so on, so on.
So, if the mind sees the truth of it,
and therefore analysis falls away,
then what is the mind to do with the content?
You...
A. Yes, I do see that.
K. We know what the content is,
we don't have it to be described.
Now, what is it to
do? It has to be emptied.
Otherwise it is mere continuity.
A. No, there is no
use analysing what is already there,
because that will not change what is there,
in any way, shape or form.
That seems to be very, very plain.
K. Plain.
A. Although we...
Perhaps you would, for a moment, explain why
we simply refuse to see that.
We do believe that an analytical enquiry
is ordered to a revelation.
K. No, sir, you can see it in a minute.
Analysis implies the analyser and the analysed.
The analyser is the analysed.
A. Yes, we are back to the observed word.
K. Obviously. I am analysing my anger.
Who is the analyser?
Part of the fragment which is anger.
So, the analyser pretends to be different.
From the analysed.
But when I see the truth
that the analyser is the analysed,
then a totally different action takes place.
Then there is no conflict
between the analyser and the analysed.
There is instant action, a perception,
which is the ending and going beyond the what is.
A. The reason I asked for the explanation
was because of the concern raised earlier about knowledge.
K. After all, the observer is knowledge.
A. Yes. I was concerned that
study in its proper form was not regarded
in the context of our discussion as unprofitable as such.
We don't mean that.
We didn't even discuss that.
K. Exactly. Yes, fine.
Well, yes, it is obvious in terms of our discussion,
but the thing that concerns me
is that so ingrained is the notion
that, for instance, in the story I told about
when I came to hear you years ago,
I began doing analysis while
I was listening to your words
and consequently I could hardly end up
with anything qualitatively differently
from what I came in with.
But you see, I didn't see that at the time.
In our videotaping, our conversations here,
this will be listened to, and when we say yes,
about knowledge, this is obvious,
in the context of our conversation it is.
But then I'm thinking...
K. Not only in the context of our conversation,
it is so. A. It is as such.
K. Life is that.
A. Exactly. I couldn't agree.
But immediately I flashed back to my own behaviour
and I know that I was not alone in that
because I listened to other conversations
regarding it at the time.
But yes, I see what you
mean now about analysis as such.
It seems to me very clear.
K. Analysis implies, sir, the analyser and the analysed.
A. Precisely.
K. The analyser is the analysed.
And also analysis implies time, duration.
I must take time to unearth, to uncover,
and it takes me the rest of my life.
A. This is a confusion we have about death too,
death's relation to time.
K. That's right. I'm coming to that.
A. Yes, of course. Yes. Please do. Please.
K. Yes. So, the
mind perceiving discards analysis completely.
Not because it's not profitable,
not because it doesn't get me where I want,
but I see the impossibility
of emptying the consciousness of its content
if the mind approaches through that channel.
Analyzer, time, and the utter futility
and the utter futility at the end of forty years.
I'm still analysing.
A. And the content of my consciousness
has not qualitatively changed.
K. Changed at all.
A. No, it's become intensified in its corruption.
K. That's right.
A. Yes.
K. So, but the mind must see its content,
must be totally aware of it,
not fragments, fragments of it.
How is that to be done?
You follow, sir?
A. Yes, I do.
K. Because that's very important in relation to death.
Because content of my consciousness is consciousness.
That consciousness is me, my ego,
my saying, I and you, we and they,
whether they are the communists, they are the Catholics,
they are the Protestants or the Hindus, they and we.
So, it is very important to find out
whether it's possible to empty consciousness of its content,
which means the dying to the me.
You follow?
A. Yes, I do.
K. Because that is the me.
A. This is where the terror starts.
K. That's where the terror starts.
A. Precisely. There's the intuition that if I die
to the content of this consciousness,
that I am wiped out.
I, who have worked,
who have lived a righteous life or an unrighteous life,
who have done so much mischief or good,
I have struggled to better myself,
I have been so kind,
so gentle, so angry, so bitter.
And when you say, empty your consciousness,
it means you are asking me to better yourself.
You are asking me to die to all that.
So, you are touching at the very root of fear.
A. Yes, exactly.
K. At the root of terror of not being.
And – yes, that's it, sir.
And I want to immortalise – that's me.
I do it through books,
writing a book and say, famous book.
Or I paint.
Or through paint, through works, through good acts,
through building this or that,
I immortalise myself.
A. This has very pernicious effects within the family.
Because we must have a son
in order to immortalise the name in time.
K. Therefore the family becomes a danger.
A. Exactly.
K. So, look what we have done, sir.
The ancient Egyptians immortalised them, sir,
made their life immortal by thinking, carrying on.
A. Perpetuating.
K. Perpetuating.
And the robbers come and tear it all to pieces.
Tutankhamun means merely a mask now,
a golden mask with a mummy.
A golden mask with a mummy.
And so on.
So, man has sought immortality through works,
through every way to find that which is immortal.
That is, beyond mortality.
Right?
A. It's a very remarkable thing that the word immortal
is a negative.
K. Negative, yes. Not mortal.
A. Yes. It's not saying what it is.
K. We are going to find out what it is.
A. Good.
K. You follow, sir, this is a very serious thing.
It isn't a plaything between two people
who are enjoying discussion,
it's a tremendously important thing.
A. Yes. I was laughing...
K. Oh, I'm not...
A. ...at the irony of it.
That inherent in the structure of that word
there is a warning,
and we just go right through the red light.
K. Right.
A. Yes. Please, please go on.
K. So, what is immortality?
Not the book.
A. Oh, no.
K. Not the painting which I have done,
not going to the moon and
putting some idiotic flag up there.
Not living a righteous life,
or not living a righteous life.
So, what is immortality?
The cathedrals are beautiful,
marvellous cathedrals,
in stone, earthquake comes, gone.
You build, you carve out of marble
a marvellous thing of Michelangelo,
earthquake, fire, destroyed,
some lunatic comes on with
a hammer and breaks it up.
So, it is in none of those.
Right?
A. Right.
K. Because that is capable of being destroyed.
Every statue becomes a dead thing,
every poem, every painting.
So, then one asks, what is immortality?
It's not in the building,
not in the building.
Just see it, sir.
It's not in the cathedral,
it's not in the saviour which you have invented,
which thought has invented,
not in the gods that man
has created out of his own image.
Then what is immortality?
Because that is related to consciousness and to death.
Unless I find that out, death is a terror.
A. Of course.
Of course.
K. I have tried to immortalise myself,
become immortal by the thought that there is a Brahman,
there is a God, there is eternity,
there is a nameless one,
and I will do everything to approach him.
I will do everything to approach him,
therefore I will lead a righteous life,
therefore I will pray, I will beg, I will obey,
I will live a life of poverty, chastity,
and so on, so on, so on,
in order to have that immortal reality with me.
But I know all that is the born of thought.
Right, sir?
A. Yes.
K. Wait, sir. See what happens.
So I see thought and its products
are the children of barren women.
A. Precisely.
K. See what is taking place.
Then what is immortality?
Right.
The beauty in the Church, not I built the Church.
The beauty in the Cathedral, the beauty in the poem,
the beauty in the sculpture.
The beauty.
Not the object of beauty.
A. Not the object.
K. The beauty itself.
That is immortal.
And I cannot grasp that,
the mind cannot grasp it,
because beauty is not in the field of consciousness.
A. You see, what you've said, again,
stands it all on its head.
We think when something dies
that we have cherished, that it is beautiful,
that beauty dies in some sense
with that which has passed away.
Actually, it's the feeling of being bereft of that beauty
that I regarded as my privilege
to have personal access to,
the belief that that has perished,
not simply been lost,
because what is lost is, by its nature,
predisposed to be found,
but to perish is to
be wiped out utterly, isn't it?
And so the belief is deep.
K. Oh, very, very.
A. Extremely deep with respect
to what we mean by perish.
In fact, the word isn't used very often, it's frightening.
It's a very frightening word.
We always talk about losing things.
Hardly ever do we say something perishes.
Now, back to what I mentioned
about standing it on its head.
The image came to my mind as a metaphor,
I hope not one of
those images we've been talking about,
that beauty, rather than being imprisoned
and therefore taken down to the utter depths of nullity
when the thing perishes,
has simply let it go.
In some sense, beauty has let this expression go.
That is upside down from what is usually thought.
K. I know, I know.
And it's probably let it go precisely on time.
That's what's so marvellous. Yes.
So, immortality, we have said,
is within the field of time.
A. The one field.
K. Right? A. Yes.
K. The field of time.
And death is also then in the field of time.
Because I have created through thought the things of time.
And death is the ending or the
beginning of a state which is timeless.
Of that I am frightened.
So, I want everything preserved in the field of time.
You follow, sir? A. Yes, we think it could be.
K. And that is what we call immortal.
The statue, the poem, the church, the cathedral.
And I see also all that is corruptible, destroyed
by one accident or by an earthquake.
Everything is gone.
So, immortality is not within the field of time.
And time is thought.
A. Of course. Yes, that follows.
K. Of course. So, anything that thought creates
must be within the field of time.
And yet thought is trying to seek immortality,
which is immortality of itself
and the things it has created.
You see, you...
So, then the problem is,
can the mind see all this?
See it, not imagine that it is seeing it.
A. No, actually see it.
Yes, the remark I made before,
when you began saying the field of time,
and I said the one field,
I didn't mean that the field of time,
as you have described it, is the one field,
but that we could be so appallingly mistaken and blind...
K. ...ignorant.
A. ...that the field of time is another fragment
and it is the only field.
And what really struck me was this misuse of thought
generates the most appalling avarice.
K. Yes, sir.
A. It's... I'm walling myself up in stone.
Yes, please.
K. So, the mind perceiving all this,
if it is alert, if it has been watchful,
all the time that we have been discussing,
it must inevitably see the whole content exposed
without any effort.
It's like reading a map.
You spread it out and look.
But if you want to go in a direction,
then you don't look at the whole map.
Then you say, I want
to go from here to there,
the direction is there so many miles,
and you don't look the rest.
What we are asking is, no direction, but just look.
Look at the content of your consciousness
without direction, without choice.
Be aware of it without any exertion of discernment.
Be choicelessly aware of this extraordinary map.
Then that choiceless awareness
gives you the tremendous energy to go beyond it.
But you need energy to go beyond it.
A. This leads me to the notion of reincarnation
that we began to touch on a little earlier.
I see the demonic root in that.
K. You see, reincarnate next life.
Nobody says, incarnate now.
A. Yes, exactly.
K. You follow, sir? A. Yes, I do.
K. You can only incarnate now
when you die to the content.
You can be reborn, regenerated totally
if you die to the content.
Yes, yes.
And there is a terrible truth on the dark side,
the demonic side, to this doctrine of reincarnation,
because if that content of consciousness
is not emptied out, then it must prevail.
K. So what happens?
A. Then it really does. Yes.
K. It prevails. So what happens?
I do not know, as a
human being, how to empty this thing.
I am not even interested. I am only frightened.
A. Only scared to death. K. Scared to death.
And I preserve something, and I die, I am burnt,
or buried underground.
The content goes on.
As we said, the content
of me is your content also.
It is not so very different.
No, no, no, no.
Slightly modified, slightly exaggerated,
given certain tendencies which depend on
your conditioning of environment, so on, so on.
But it is essentially the same consciousness.
Unless a human being empties that consciousness,
that consciousness goes on like a river,
collecting, accumulating, all that is going on.
And out of that river comes the expression
or the manifestation of the one that is lost,
when the mediums, seances, all those say,
say, your brother, your uncle, your wife is here,
what has happened is they have manifested themselves
out of that stream which is the continuous consciousness
of struggle, pain, unhappiness, all that.
And a man who has observed
and has looked at the consciousness and empties it,
he doesn't belong to that stream at all.
Then he is living each moment anew,
because he is dying each moment. You understand?
A.S. – Oh yes, I do.
K. – There is no accumulation of the me
which has to be expressed. He is dying every minute,
living every minute and dying every minute.
And therefore in that there is
– what shall I say? –
there is no content. You follow, sir?
It is like a tremendous energy in action.
A.S. – This gives a totally different understanding
of what we mean by the phrase, in the afterlife.
On the one hand, there is this continuity
in disordered content of consciousness,
K. It is totally disordered. That's right.
A.S. – which is not radically affected, qualitatively,
with respect to its nature,
simply because somebody has stopped breathing for good.
No, it's on its way.
And therefore the attempt that is often made
on the part of persons
to contact this stream of consciousness
after the death of a person,
when made within the same quality of consciousness,
attains nothing but a reinforcement
within their own personal life,
and it does a terrible
thing to that content of consciousness
which has gone on, since
it also feeds that some more.
K. That's right. Yes, I do see that.
K. A person came to see
me, and his wife was dead,
and he really thought he loved her.
So he said, I must see my wife again.
Can you help me?
I said, which wife do you want to see?
The one that cooked?
The one that bore the children?
The one that gave you sex?
The one that quarrelled with you?
The one that dominated you, frightened you?
He said, I don't want to meet any of those.
I want to meet the good of her.
You follow, sir?
The image of the good
he has built out of her.
None of the ugly things,
or what he considered ugly things,
but the idea of the good
which he had culled out of her,
and that is the image he wants to meet.
I said, don't be infantile.
You are so utterly immature
when you have slept with
her, and got angry with her.
All that you don't want,
you want just the image
which you have about her goodness.
I said, and you know, sir, he began to cry,
really cry for the first time.
He said, afterwards I have cried when she died,
but the tears were of self-pity, my loneliness,
my sense of inertia, you follow, lack of things.
Now I am crying, I have cried
because I see what I have done.
You understand, sir?
A. Yes, I do.
So, to understand death there must be no fear.
The fear exists and the terror of it exists
only when the content is not understood.
And the content is the me.
He is the me.
And the me is the chair. You follow, sir?
The thing I am attached to. It is so stupid.
And I am frightened of that.
The bank account, the family, you follow?
A. Oh yes, yes I do.
K. Unless one is really deeply serious in this matter,
you can't incarnate now,
in the deep sense of that word,
and therefore immortality is in the book,
in the statue, in the cathedral,
in the things I have put together by thought.
That is all field of time.
A. Right. It just occurred to me
what a terrible thing we have been doing
so often over and over again to Plato.
By this perennial attempt, academic analysis of the text,
when he plainly said that the business of the philosopher,
by which he didn't mean the analyser
in this mad way that we
have been observing, it goes on,
the business of the philosopher,
namely the one who is concerned
with a radical change in rebirth,
which he associates with wisdom,
the business of the philosopher is to practise dying.
To practise dying.
Yes, I don't think he meant routine,
repetition of die, die, die, die, die.
I think he puts it with an ing,
because he doesn't want to fall out of act.
I know I use this phrase all the time,
but it came to me early in our conversations,
and it seems to say for
me what I want to say.
I have to say I learned it from you,
though I don't want to
put the words in your mouth.
But it's possible to fall out of act
into the terror and the demonic stream of time,
but when one is in act,
the whole thing is an ongoing movement.
K. So, sir, time has a stop. A. Precisely.
See the beauty of it, sir.
And it is that beauty which is immortal,
not the things which thought has created.
A. Right.
K. So, living is dying.
K. And love is essentially dying to the mean.
Not the things which thought has said, this is love.
Love, sex, love, pleasure, you follow? All that.
It is the dying to time is love.
So, living, love and death are one thing,
not divisive, not separated, not divorced,
not in the field of time,
but it is completely a living, moving thing, indivisible.
And that is immortal.
So, now, most of us are educated wrongly.
A. How true that is.
K. From childhood we are never taught to be serious.
From childhood we are taught the cultivation of thought,
cultivation of thought and the expression
and the marbles of thought.
All our philosophies, books, everything is based on that.
And when you say, die to all that,
you really awaken the terror of not knowing.
This gives me security in knowing.
Then knowledge becomes the field of my safety.
And you ask me, give all
that up, die to all that.
I say, you are insane.
How can I die to that?
That is part of me.
A. There is a very, very beautiful Zen saying
that seems to relate to this.
When it is understood correctly,
it speaks of jumping off the cliff with hands free.
Jumping off the cliff with hands free.
The hands that hold,
always grasping the past or reaching out towards the future,
and we never get off that horizontal track.
It is like a Lionel train, forever goes on.
So then comes the question,
what is living in the present?
Death is the future.
And I have lived for forty years, all the accumulated...
What is the present?
The present is the death of the content.
And I don't know, it
has got immense beauty in that.
Because that means no conflict.
You follow, sir?
No tomorrow.
If you tell a man who loves,
who is going to enjoy
that man or woman next, tomorrow,
when you say there is no tomorrow,
he says, what are you talking about?
A. Yes, I know.
Sometimes you will say, when you have said something,
it sounds absurd.
And of course, in relation to
the way we have been taught
to do analysis, it sounds absurd.
K. There, sir.
Can we educate children, students,
to live totally differently?
Live and understand and act with this sense of
understanding the content and the beauty of it all.
A. If I have understood you correctly,
there is only one answer to that question.
Yes. Yes.
Sounds...
I think the word here wouldn't be absurd,
it would be something like wild.
Yes.
I see now what you mean about death and birth
as non-temporarily related,
in terms of the question that we raised
about their relation earlier.
Because when you say there is this incarnation
now upon the instant...
K. No, if you see the beauty of it, sir,
the thing takes place.
A. Then it has happened.
K. It is not the result of mentation,
it is not the result of man's thinking, thinking, thinking.
It is actual perception of what is.
A. And the amazement that it
is the same energy at root
doesn't take something over here,
that's a different energy called God.
K. No, no, outside agency brought in here.
It is the same wasted energy, dissipated energy,
which is no longer dissipated.
Therefore it is...
A. Exactly.
This throws totally...
I am beginning now to use the words
absolutely and totally,
because we are in the academy, you know,
we are advised to be very careful of.
K. I know, I know.
A. But I am sorry about all that.
The fact remains that it is total, it is total.
There is a total change.
And the transformation...
من
كل
شخص
is not within the field of time and knowledge.
A.S. – Is not within
the field of time and knowledge.
K.K. – You see how you relate.
A.S. – Yes, and then the profound seriousness of it
that attends when one sees the
rest of that sentence of yours.
It is the responsibility of each.
And if I may add just one other thing here,
because it seems to me that it's coming together,
that it isn't the responsibility of one
over against the other to do something.
It is to come with and to,
as the other is coming to and with,
and we begin together to have a look.
K.K. – Share together, learn together.
A.S. – Just quietly having a look.
And in that activity, which is not planned,
one of the amazing things about this conversation is
that it, to use your beautiful word, flowers.
It doesn't require an imposition without,
of a contrivance, of a management.
Somehow it grows out of itself.
It's this thing of growing out of itself
that relates to this thing
that you've been talking about in consciousness.
By pointing to the head
I don't mean consciousness up here.
But it's the out of itself that it all...
it's like that water that turns in on itself.
K.K. – It remains water.
A.S. – It remains water, exactly.
This has been a wonderful revelation,
the whole thing about death, living and love.
I do hope when we have our next conversation
that we could begin to pursue this
in relation to education even further.
K.K. – Further, yes, sir.